[Music]
the stoa
is a digital campfire where we cohere in
dialogue
about what matters most at the knife's
edge of what's happening now
[Music]
boom the problem with playing good music
at the store is that you just want to
keep listening to it
but we have to begin uh today uh because
we have a special
guest with us so first welcome to the
stoa everyone i'm the steward of the
stoa peter limberg
and stoa is a place for us to go here
and dialogue
about what matters most at the knight's
edge of this very moment
and today is part of the sense maker in
residence series
and this is um an invitation for sense
makers to come in
for a month for four sessions same time
each week same day
to try to make sense on a certain theme
and topic with us and the idea is to
evolve
the conversation together uh and today
we have psychological superstar
greg henriquez uh greg is the professor
uh for the combined integrated doctoral
program
at james madison university he created
something called unified theory of
knowledge this series uh
is going to talk about his framework
both in terms of the meta crisis
and kind of the opportunities for wisdom
that our digital age affords us
so that is quite exciting um
and the mc of this series each of these
series has their own emcee
that was siri just kind of like talking
to me
um so we got uh anjin kara uh
today a stoa super user uh kind of a
wild man so i'm uh
five percent nervous handing over the
the emceeing keys to him
but uh it feels right at the same time
uh so i'm gonna take in
engine in a moment engine's going to
maybe introduce greg a little bit the
session and the uh
questionnaire protocols and then we'll
go from there and this is uh 75 minutes
today but uh next week or the next three
sessions might be 90 minutes
that being said i'll take in punjin
oh i it would be helpful if i allowed
people to unmute themselves
okay so uh there you go
hey guys how you doing um peter didn't
tell the entire truth
siri was actually his first choice but
uh wasn't the most cooperative at asking
complicated questions so
that's what i was brought in this is
exciting
my dad's a psychiatrist i grew up in a
house full of psychology textbooks
and you have a pile over there that are
about young
you have a pile over here about the
brain and you have a pile over there
that's about jonathan hype
and you just be like wait they they all
say different things
and the dinner table often was my dad
being like wait
none of this makes sense sometimes i
pick from there sometimes they pick from
that
and so psychology for me in a very
visceral sense has been this
multiple piles of books around my house
that didn't talk to each other
um i found out about greg reading a book
about adhd
and it was talking about a similar thing
where in adhd there's so many different
theories
from the brain to neuroscience to the
social aspect to development
once again not much of it talked to each
other and one of the authors
quoted greg and said hey there's this
interesting guy
i couldn't pronounce his name at the
time but han rakes 2011.
with his unified theory of psychology
it seemed grandiose and i was like
pretty skeptical
but it's pretty stunning to see what
greg has accomplished
he has this sketch on his website where
he's got in 1997 he's
done a little pencil sketch of what the
theory of knowledge is
um to see in 2020 people on youtube and
the internet finding out about him
is just marvelous because the tok for me
in that second was
oh my god those are all the books in my
house coming together
finally somebody's put it together so
greg excited to have you on
um the way the session's gonna go is 75
minutes
greg's gonna do a lecture then we'll
have a q a afterwards um
feel free to put your questions in the
chat and i'll pick the ones that get
upvoted
um do a plus one if you see a question
for the first time what could be helpful
for me
is if you see a plus one if you instead
of just writing plus one again if you
can make it plus two
and if you see a plus two make it plus
three it's gonna make it easier for me
to see the most uploaded questions
um let's try that out and
um there's gonna be four sessions and
greg take it away all right man hey that
was uh
thank you uh that's very uh warming
of my heart and soul right off the bat
man so i appreciate that
um you know it's good to see somebody
else's living the problem of psychology
with all the damn piles of books and
brain
and young and jonathan height i love
that you know
um and uh yeah that happened to me in
the mid 1990s
uh it made my head explode and then i
was like well
what the hell you know why is there so
much chaos
i went down a rabbit hole and uh
found something perhaps and uh and
really happy to be here to share it it's
wonderful to be at the nice edge
that's why i always want to try to be in
so it's a great opportunity
um and i look forward to these four
sessions so what i what i had planned
was uh yeah i was going to run through
maybe a 45 minute lecture or so
um but certainly you know we can stop it
very i got various places where you
could stop and
and dialogue uh give you an overview
about what i'm looking at in relation
but it's also you know iterative process
i've really
enjoyed all the conversations that i've
been with you know schmachtenberger i
know daniel gortz is going bonnie
uh bonnie's happening i listened to
zach's you know
so many brilliant people here i'm just
really honored to be a part of it so
thank you peter for the invite um and i
look forward to
sharing with you my version of reality
and hopefully it can
add some a little bit of wisdom uh to
the chaotic world that we
find ourselves in so i'll go ahead and
share my screen
okay um hope folks can see this all
right
um so here's my tentative game plan um
so what i'm gonna give you today uh just
sort of is a flashbang tour of the
garden
all right uh so my garden is a my
religion that's not a religion
uh you hear john vervicky and uh jordan
hall talk about that
and i want to share with you why uh
i fell into from in the mid 2000s a new
atheist view
into what would be sort of a
naturalistic spiritual view
um and some of my connections in
relationship to that some of the
symbolism that's in the
why the hell i created a cartoon out of
my theory um certainly my dad wondered
about that
and he's professor of history what the
hell are you doing i was like i don't
know
but it's a calling okay and then i want
to share with you why that is
um next week i was thinking i would dive
into justification
systems all right uh obviously peter
lindbergh
uh shot across uh the culture
consciousness with culture war 2.0
um and the explosion of different mean
plexus
and uh i can help frame that in terms of
systems of justification
and make a connection between human
consciousness and our
run around on this planet as persons and
trying to justify why the hell we're
doing what we're doing
um and what that means for the chaotic
wave of fluctuation that we're seeing in
the various paradigms
gi dynamics places the systems of
justification
on our investment and influence patterns
that's what the ii
stands for so we're investing and
influencing
and justifying and that intersection of
justification investment and influence
you want to understand human behavior
dynamics that's a pretty good way in my
opinion to do so
um and then the third session uh
i'm going to talk about the problem of
psychology i'm completely obsessed with
this thing called the problem of
psychology
uh and uh following my good friend zach
stein in his brilliant four-part series
and
learned a lot about the tripartite view
of skill development
uh insolvent and transcendence which i
think provides a brilliant humanistic
educational frame of reference for how
we might
cultivate ourselves in this time between
worlds um
i i want to riff off to some of that and
then offer my version of reality
in relation and uh my location is really
and zach nailed us in his uh
actually i think he was responding to
anjen uh nailed in his response and said
hey greg's working in the science domain
okay and academia um which yeah i've
been banging my head up again
again see academy now for 20 years um
so uh the i i look forward to dialoguing
about that
and then finally we'll see where
questions are i can come in and riff on
the last session
uh i also have some ideas for meta psych
tech
um so jordan hall john verbaki uh
got together and you know
uh john was talking about the psycho
technologies that we need and then
jordan was talking about coherence and
it was like hey man we need a
metapsychology tech
uh system it's like well you know for
last 20 years in many ways that's
essentially what
my journey has uh uh pushed me into
and as a function of that i can talk to
you about how i'm thinking about
metapsych tech in general
and at the same time you know if we've
hit on a lot of conversations
um uh then we can just riff and jam and
i'm
good with that so that's the basic game
plan of the month
um you know this is a 21st century
vision of wisdom
i'm not going to be talking an enormous
amount about wisdom
uh you know there's a whole this now in
the last 10 years 20 years
been an academic enterprise to try to
delineate
what is wisdom where does it come from
what are its elements
um i'm basically i'm going to offer you
a quick frame of reference on wisdom i'm
happy to talk about wisdom
for me the short summary of wisdom
is the cultivation of knowledge and
practices that lead to value states of
being
okay um so fundamentally that's uh what
i am after
and so our question is given the current
state of affairs that we find ourselves
in what are the sense making knowledge
systems
uh and the cultivation practices that
lead to what we
can reflect on and of course be open to
changing uh to be our valued
states of being so that's fundamentally
what this is about
is about sharing with you my uh
sense-making
uh if we get into practices uh what i
use as a psychotherapist
as a neurotic son of a you know
all that to help
uh cultivate a sense of being in this
world that has purpose
uh matters uh seems to add some
well-being
uh to self and others so
um i wanna start off a little bit to
help folks
uh my system uh this thing i want to
offer you some thoughts on groking this
thing at least to enter into it because
a lot of people will experience my
system as a bit of a maze or a cathedral
it's got a lot of twists and turns it's
got a lot of references
embedded in it so i want to at least
start off and try to open up
a frame of reference to this big system
uh
unified theory of knowledge so we'll
have some ideas about growth in the
system
and then that means we have to say what
exactly is this system
um so it's the overarching term uh
for this uh you know kind of behemoth
network a cathedral of ideas
is the unified theory of knowledge uh to
grok the you talk it's helpful to start
thinking of it as a unified theory of
knowledge
tree of knowledge system okay
and the word tree has got to play on
several different meanings
so the first meeting is this this
cartoon
uh depiction of a tree uh
that can be thought of as the unified
theory of knowledge tree
um it can also be thought of as the me a
tua tok tree which me
stands for metaphysical empirical and
yes this is a yin yang symbol with
little knees around it
it also spells out meme if you pay
attention to it
me i mean there's a unified theory
a unified approach and a theory of
knowledge embedded
in the structures the unified theory of
psychology a unified approach to
psychotherapy
one of which is a pure reason the other
is a practical reason that merges
philosophy and psychology together
into a new theory of knowledge
um on the unified theory of knowledge
tree are eight branches and this is
where it gets kind of confusing
the tree of knowledge system represents
the first branch
on the unified theory of knowledge tree
uh to understand that is understand my
history uh this was actually even
discussed a little bit it was in 1997
that actually the four
cones uh you know i just fired it up one
day and four cones fell out of my head
and my life hasn't been the same ever
since back in 1997
so for four years i worked on and really
elaborated and then ultimately published
in 2003 that
the tree of knowledge system at that
time i'm really
basically trying to essentially grok
natural science
and do so in a way that allows me to
make sense of the science of psychology
that's my first
um sort of uh vision not a small task by
any set
but this view of of knowledge and cosmic
evolution allows me
a new way to sort the variables uh and
extract meaning
um but it's awesome and ultimately what
i would now call sort of as
modern empirical natural science meaning
uh
if those of you familiar with big
history it's essentially a map of big
history
in a way that solves the problem of
psychology
and i now recently refer to this as
men's knowledge that's modern
empirical natural scientific knowledge
uh that started in 1997 however from
really it launched a different kind of
frame of reference that i'll be sharing
with you in relationship to the garden
okay the unified theory of knowledge is
a wisdom-oriented philosophy
to ground men so we need to move from
men's knowledge to women's knowledge
okay in the 21st century uh and
my wife appreciates that and has been
telling me that for a long time
um so it is a transition
uh from a scientific theory for the
science of psychology
into a scientific humanistic
wisdom-oriented
uh frame of reference that's grounded in
science
but it's also grounded in science in a
way that reaches out
to our other systems of justification
scientific systems of justification
are grounded in logos logic analysis and
attempting to get at
objectivity okay um but there are a lot
of other ways of being in the world ways
that are grounded in our humanistic
essence
uh that and have ethos and morality and
mythos
okay um so it's to rock the system you
want to understand the tree of knowledge
system is in dialectical tension
with this metaphysical empirical theory
of knowledge as a whole
and there are pure reason and practical
reason elements that are embedded in it
it's also the case that i want to make a
acknowledgement here that there's a
connection
uh between this version of reality and
the bible of course
you can't help but know it's a tree of
knowledge
system if you know any sunday school um
and uh
obviously then you have a tree in a
garden um
and i'll just also make a tie-in uh so
here's jordan peterson
uh who i really uh appreciate his bible
series
uh he opens up his bible series talking
about
genesis okay and notes a very powerful
fact
uh that the christian interpretation of
genesis has this part of john
uh in the beginning there was the word
uh
and george peterson offers i think a
brilliant analysis
of genesis uh the fall uh the nature of
self-consciousness and what it speaks to
us in terms of mythos
i encourage you to check out that aspect
of his work
and it is an aspect that i speak to
metaphorically in the naming of the tree
of knowledge
uh that is ultimately we need to come to
a place that we have eaten off the tree
of knowledge
and we need to learn how to healthily
eat off the tree of knowledge and
ultimately do so to cultivate a garden
for ourselves for our communities for
our nation-states and for the globe
ultimately uh in the 21st century and
that is essentially the wisdom task
uh certainly in the western intellectual
tradition
that i see us as confronting with and
ultimately my system
is really about my version of reality as
to how that might be accomplished
so what i'm now going to do then is i'm
going to do
give you the flash uh and then i'm going
to stop and then we'll pause and i'll
see where questions are
things like that so um what am i
basically this next two minutes what i'd
like everybody to do is just take a deep
breath
get centered okay those of you that know
uh ken wilbur talk a lot about vision
logic you know that there are different
ways of processing information
we can process information
linguistically and we can pre-practice
information through
perceptual reasoning gestalts
so what i'm going to do is give you a
really fast two-minute
perceptual reasoning gestalt and then we
can come back and talk
uh about the various parts about this
okay so this is my 21st century vision
of wisdom in two minutes
so
alrighty there it is so
what i'd like to do now is just come
back i'm going to stop sharing the
screen for a sec
and see um uh let's see
anjin uh i'll check in with you
and see if you have thoughts about
any questions at this point i'm going to
take or i can jump back in and then do
the more detailed analysis of the garden
it's the game plan
but i figured i'd just pause here for a
second
and engage and see uh what your thoughts
are on jim
um does anybody have any questions
okay uh greg if i
if i could throw my two cents in i think
when i first approached your work i got
overwhelmed when i
came across the garden like it was a lot
of information for me
yeah i think what helped me was you had
this story
of just the t okay like kind of the big
history story
i'm curious if you'd you'd want to start
with
just focusing on that or that framing if
that would be of interest to you
and then kind of expand to that sure
absolutely
yeah um
let me go ahead and uh yeah let me i
have to pull up a
powerpoint in relationship to that okay
um
but uh that's that's definitely to
organize the
frame of reference the reason i didn't
actually start there was because uh
i was back at the store i don't know i
think it was in remember exactly what
the hell it was june or something
um and i did do a tok on that uh that
was sort of the focus
but it probably would help to go back
and just have some frame of reference in
relationship to that
uh so let me pull that up and give a
little frame on that okay
that's something reasonable all right
so uh let me find it real fast
and i'll be right there
okay
all right let me share screen
okay so what i'm going to do is i'll
then walk you through just sort of the
basics of the first part of this
set of ideas the thing that portal that
got me
involved in it i'll share my screen
okay okay um
so the tree of knowledge system all
right uh provides a framework
a novel framework for us to think about
ways in which we want to map
both reality okay and our scientific
knowledge of that reality
that's one of the things that is
important to realize about the system
uh is because i came to the system i'm a
psychologist not a physicist
okay um but what i did then is i sort of
cracked the code or at least it's my
through the process by which humans
justify okay
by realizing then uh those of you that
are familiar with john verveigh's
uh system will know that he divides
human knowing up into four different ps
we have a base of procedural knowing
sort of the the most basic we
learn habits we learn basic frames of
reference and then we can engage in
procedural knowing
he talks about perspectival knowing
talks about participatory knowing
i would argue that we should pre-mates
okay but we humans also have another
fourth p
uh it's propositional knowing uh that's
basically the process by which we
uh semantically represent uh knowledge
claims
uh and really what i did is with
justification systems theory i developed
a theory of propositional knowing and
its implication in terms of how it will
take off
i did that in 1996 and it was because i
then
cleaved the culture person part of us in
terms of the way
propositions are organized from the
primate part of us
okay which are perspectival procedural
participatory knowing systems
it fundamentally then set the stage for
me to sort of grok the way people know
and then flip that back on and say well
if this is the way individuals know
then what are our justification systems
for
um in various domains one of which can
then be science
um so uh here's the tree of knowledge
system
it's a new map of cosmic evolution uh
when you use the term cosmic evolution
uh that's basically a depiction of uh
the universe
starting 13.7 13.8 billion years ago
um in the context of what might be
considered i prefer to call it an energy
singularity
um off the energy singularity there's an
evolution
of behavioral complexity which i will
walk you through
okay um the tree of knowledge is a
theory of our antic reality why that i
mean the reality independent of our
beliefs
and our scientific knowledge of it it
attempts to offer a consilient worldview
the term consilience comes from a man by
the name of edward wilson a famous
uh big picture naturalist who wanted a
way
to build the bridges between uh the
natural sciences the human
social sciences and the humanities in
1998 he produced a book called
consilience the unity of knowledge
and the tree of knowledge system one
thing that
wilson didn't solve or address was the
problem of psychology
and the tree of knowledge fundamentally
is about
that um it provides a view i think that
allows us to understand
uh how complexity emerges all the way
from quantum mechanics all
to sociology it describes a language
system for defining behavior mind and
science that's actually where the root
uh key issues of defining what
psychology are
it offers a novel way to think about
cosmic evolution across four the
dimensions linked by four joint points
um and i think very importantly for
stowa
is the scientific sense and meaning
making system and what i mean by that is
you know look around look at the
information ecologies we have brilliant
people like daniel schmuckenberger doing
a huge amount
of wonderful work in sense-making you
know what the hell is science i'm my
brother who's like
scientists don't know anything because
the you know the coveted scenario and
everything else
and it's like you have to understand
what science
knows okay relative to what's
unbelievably speculative
relative to all sorts of different
political chaotic and not to mention a
nefarious information environment when
people are trying to manipulate
and distort we need systems to actually
then say well
hey man you know uh i'll say this system
fell out of me in about four seconds
and it really is just elaborated on its
sense there's been very little
fluctuation
uh as a function of this so there are
you know we're not going to go back to
thinking the earth is six thousand years
old i mean
evolution is here to stay um and this
adopt
the periodic table of the elements uh is
pretty rock solid
there are ways to consolidate our
scientific knowledge
they were best theories together at
least that's what i'm positioning
uh this so um when i talk about
antic reality i mean that i'm uh i'm
inside science now science operates from
a particular kind of
realism uh the realism of science is
that there isn't
uh reality that's independent of our
knowledge of it now those of you
familiar with quantum mechanics and
general relativity and know that physics
uh went from
a complete independence of observer
observed uh
into systems that actually have to get
entangled as it were especially in
quantum but both in
general relativity also um so there are
lots of interesting questions about the
relationship between observer and
observed
but fundamentally the scientific system
of justification
is that there is an antic reality um and
that there
are ontological theories of that reality
and that there are systems of
epistemological justification
so modern empirical natural science says
hey
you have to have data you have to then
engage and once you engage in data you
engage in experimentation
the tree of knowledge says that the the
grammar of science
uh offers what's called an exterior
epistemology means it's
it operates from a third person
generalized view and it divides the
world up into objects fields and change
uh these are the fundamental elements of
us of the grammar of science um
that's really important to me as a
psychologist uh because there are some
people out there that argue that
psychology
is the science of behavior okay
if if you're following me then you think
about the idea that psychology is the
signs of behavior like wait a minute
behavior goes all the way down okay
behavior goes all the way down into
physics
uh and so the issue uh that
psychologists get cons confused about
is they then fail to separate uh key
b uh issues of ontology which is the
claims about reality
from epistemology which is the process
by which we
know about that reality so anyway the
bottom line is the tree of knowledge
offers a theory of modern empirical
scientific knowledge
it argues that we can describe object
field change into four
different uh dimensions of complexity
known as matter
that's the first dimension which emerges
out of a pure energy singularity
life mind and culture
and that this represents an unfolding
wave of behavior
writ large and one of the novel things
about it then
is that it then maps the antique reality
of matter like mind and culture
uh and posits that we can arrange four
broad domains of psychology of the
sciences
in relation so the physical sciences
correspond to matter
biological sciences correspond to life
now that's standard
okay what happens in science is that
then you get into neuroscience that's
still real science and stem
and then you move into psychology and
the hits the fan
and what i mean by that is then every
there's an enormous amount
of dispute and difference so much so
that you ask john
uh john verbaki there's an entire branch
of understanding called cognitive
science
that breaks off some psychology and
tries to be its own thing
the reason cognitive science emerges is
precisely because psychology is such a
well anjan said it you know it's in such
a fragmented mess
i would argue that cognitive science
basically inherits the same basic
problems
uh although it's more somewhat more
unified it finds itself in a very very
fragmented
place because we're lacking a
fundamental sense-making system that
allows us to get the grammar and
language correct
so the basics of the tree of knowledge
is the emergence
out of a pure energy singularity we can
talk about this how this might
have a first inflationary reaction
inside the energy singularity
that begins a massive process of
expansion and differentiation
okay and then ultimately this explodes
into
the matter dimension the matter
dimension
refers to uh at the basis quantum
mechanics across scaleless general
relativity
and up in terms of the complexity and
arrangement of objects goes into
chemistry
there are certainly other very complex
objects like the earth can be thought of
as a complex object
but that relates to the size and
multiplicity of it
then we see about 4 billion years ago
3.8 billion years ago
there's the miracle of life the spark of
life
we talk about exactly what happens there
but fundamentally there's an inside and
outside of a cell organized around a
lipid membrane
somehow there's a correspondence between
a storage of data information
dna and then r maybe rna initially and
then into dna
that allows for an intergenerational
transmission and then there are
metabolic processes that do work
to maintain uh differentiation
replication
metabolism etc lots of fascinating ideas
about what gave rise to life
once it gets started we see the
explosion of prokaryotic cells as
cells with out of nucleus and then into
more advanced
bigger cells big life shortly after big
life emerges
uh we see another tremendous shift uh
one of the kingdoms splits off
uh so you have kingdoms of plants and
kingdoms of fungi as
big life and then you get the animal
kingdom
about 550 million years ago animals get
organized into complex
active bodies that are then coordinated
by brains and nervous systems
it is that process that the tree of
knowledge introduces the kind
capital m mind so the term mind is to
refer to the third dimension of
behavioral complexity
the third plane of existence okay so i
look over here i see my fish swimming
around
in the language of the tree of knowledge
capital m mind i'm observing their
mind as they swim around just as though
you'd look at a living flower
and you say oh that's alive okay
why do i can explain why we need this
word
mind um and what it does is it solves a
lot of the split
uh and confusion around what
consciousness is and what behavior is
in psychology
but then uh we fast forward to about a
hundred thousand years ago
uh and you see the evolution from
insects and
fish into birds uh and mammals
and then uh we see ultimately one
particular primate
um adopts yet another interacting
information processing communication
system in the in the form of language
um that explodes there's a thing called
the justification hypothesis that i was
going to talk about next time
provides a frame of reference for
understanding why over the last 100 000
years
our system of being uh
has escalated and so dramatically
changed uh the balance of power
um and the tok system as i mentioned
already then says
as part of that evolution of
justification which dates back
you know 75 000 years et cetera clearly
is in
in process 50 000 years ago we see an
emergence and then 12 000 years ago we
see agriculture
uh it starts to merge with technology in
particular ways and particular kind of
justification system
that we call science emerges out of that
and then functions to map the evolution
of complexity
so it's a theory on the right hand side
of scientific knowledge
or scientific ontological claims
justified by scientific epistemology
that then uh map the antic reality of
matter like mind and culture
and then here's a diagram so the blue is
that antic reality
and the red is the scientific onto
epistemology
what that means is is that basically
what we should be really instilling is a
return to what ken wilber called the
perennial philosophy
okay the great chain of being that
before it got messed with
um uh christianity the great chain of
bean was basically
there are rocks there are plants
there are animals and there are people
uh that great chain of bean really comes
from aristotle
and virtually every philosophy every
culture
that's ever been studied categorizes the
world
up into these four different categories
now what happened with modern science
is they showed that the simple
classification of rocks plants animals
people doesn't work
kind of like earth wind air and fire uh
and therefore as a function of it being
not working it got lost um or
and then was seen as simplistic and
needed to be upgraded
okay but the question was well actually
we can now
fill in the gaps and understand the
emergences over time
and then also understand why rocks
plants animals and people
exist on different dimensions of
complexity or planes of existence
that's what the tree of knowledge
affords us many many different people
have seen this in different ways the
tree of knowledge offers a particular
kind
of explanation for this four-dimensional
reality
so what as a sense-making system
okay uh the tree of knowledge then
encourages you to then
view the world through a prism that
organizes it around
different uh frequencies material
frequencies operate at one
in one way biological living frequencies
mental animal frequencies and culture
person frequencies
and if you learn to see the world
through that particular lens
i believe that you can then derive an
enormous amount of
clarity and coherence
so i'm going to i'll stop there
and see anjan if uh
if that if there are questions that
arise out of that
um or we can uh move into a wide variety
of different
angles here given that
we got some questions in the chat just a
quick question to you greg
um what's your plan um after this little
question session do you have more to
your slides you said you wanted to talk
about
the garden yeah i mean well there's i
got
uh basically you know i know throwing a
lot out there and i basically
see what people are what's alive for
people uh you know i i can go back to
that listen obviously i flew through the
garden just to give you a little bit of
a
a run down about what that is uh it's a
cathedral i mean you know so it's like
hey you know there are lots of different
elements that we can
talk about um so that's an option we can
return to that
um but why don't i take some questions
and we'll see where
uh what feels interesting to people to
move towards and
i'll go back to that if that feels uh
where the flow takes us
um just a quick clarification question
for me then
um
like there there's this
sect of youtube that's like the way to
pick up girls is to understand
how they're evolutionarily programmed
all of a human can and there's this like
incredible reductionism
that we're just this like programmatic
beings that can only be understood
in this evolutionary lens then there's
this like
other sect of youtube that's like oh
it's all about
neuroeconomics keep the doritos in your
pantry out of sight it'll require less
willpower therefore be able to do it
easier and then jonathan hyde's work
that we talked about which is
you can really try to understand the
relational aspects and justification and
the social
aspects of it am i right to understand
the power of the tok
is to see that a human is influenced at
all of these levels
it's not this is right or that it's hey
you can understand
me by looking at each of these levels
how are the different ways
my behavior is influenced and created
yeah 100 uh so each what you have there
is each you know i use the
metaphor the elephant a lot you know the
blind men and the elephant okay
uh that is that people develop paradigms
to see particular lines of thought
uh that are useful okay um but what we
lack
is a paradigm that actually interrelates
those lines of thought
and then makes them cohere and you hear
that because then people could make
these absolutist statements
okay oh everything's due to evolution or
everything's due to neuroeconomics or
everything to do with social
construction
um and and the answer to that is
clearly not i mean just not
you know that's not the way it works um
what they what you have is you're
you're a system uh that operates at
multiple levels and dimensions
okay uh you're an integrated system that
somehow
is operating at all those dimensions
coherently
the question is how do you tease apart
those dimensions and see their inner
relation
okay that's the issue so the social
constructionist people make an
unbelievably very
point that that we come equipped as a as
a cultural primate
we come equipped to justify okay we
don't have
content of justification but we do they
don't make this point but they then
basically say well oh my god
if we're unbelievably sort of open at
the level of justification then
what our sociocultural constructs are
then we'll play a huge role
in how we dictate what's good what's
valuable what men and women should do
what do we feel about the races and of
course that's true i mean
look at you know i grew up in a
particular time
5 000 years ago if i grew up in siberia
in russia
my world view would be radically
different right okay
so my system of justification is
enormously influenced by the cultural
context
at the same time i can go and look at
people
across the wide variety of different
domains and see look hey
everywhere you go people care about sex
they care about status they care about
getting injured
you know they worry about food there's
an enormous amount of similarity too
um and there are evolutionary
similarities you know that you want to
understand through a socio-biological
level
there are neuro-based similar realities
there are operant realities that's the
scenario
particular kind of view all of those are
have validity
in themselves okay for me the question
is what's the interrelations between the
paradigms
that's the meta theoretical question and
then the real philosophical question is
what is your metaphysical language
system that you can bring to bear and
can you achieve
coherence and clarity with your language
system those are the two things that i
wrestle with most
um we got some questions from the chat
so there's
three questions that are pretty similar
rain ron and cadell
um so i'm going to call him rain first
but ron and cadel are you gonna go next
thanks um obvious question what are the
key differences between utah
and integral theory ah okay
um i i like a lot of integral theory a
lot um
and it's a couple of things that i
really love about it um
so i love ken wilbur's concern
with the material flatland and what
science did
okay in relationship to splitting off
our epistemologies
uh over emphasizing exterior
epistemologies
sacrificing or the consequence they
didn't do this really intentionally but
the consequence of scientific language
games
was to essentially undervalue uh
individual interior and collective
interior epistemologies
so so and the quadrants then return us
to goodness truth and beauty
as a holistic philosophy is required for
our fulfillment
right that's one thing you did
brilliantly in my estimation the second
thing that he does brilliantly in my
estimation
um is understand stages and developments
and line you know the line stage and in
particular
sort of the ego development uh you know
it gets a little
uh simplistic at the color level okay uh
but
you know his analysis in 2017 i think it
was about
trump and uh post-modernism and you know
about what we need is
second tier is a little bit complicated
because it talks down to people sticking
to your consciousness
all right that you've got to go into
teal and this creates all sorts of
tensions because everybody are very
sensitive to hierarchy
okay um but the idea that there's a pre
a rational and a post-trans-rational
developmental sequence
that you can see people on those places
that we want to cultivate that
particular
level of integration along those lines
is absolutely brilliant
so those are some real strengths i think
that he is
um i challenged some of him
in terms of a couple of different places
um his deep spiritual ontology
i'm more spiritually agnostic he makes
certain kinds of spiritual claims my
friend andre marquis is an integral
scholar
argues that he makes a bit of a category
error based on his own
subjective perceptions and then makes
generalized claims about the nature of
ultimate reality that's worthy of
some critique um and i also uh
basically i do a lot of work in upper
right okay
so in quadrants if you speak quadrant
language upper right what he calls
he basically creates an a material flat
land ontology
for the upper right quadrant that is
basically in my view a big mistake
uh you want to change your thinking
scientifically from
physicalism to behaviorism and then once
you go to behaviorism you can actually
get a behavioral view
of the upper right that corresponds to
phenomenology
um and social systems and culture in a
much more coherent way
so my contention is i've got an ontology
that matches epistemology
uh his ontology and epistemology
relative to science is a little clunky
seems very reasonable thank you sure
um ron you're next and then after that
it'll be cadell
thanks hey greg this tags right on to
what rayne was just asking you
and it it's another wilbur comparison
question
um just and maybe you did answer this in
a way and you were just
kind of alluding to it but just in a
very fundamental sense do you agree with
wilbur's idea that
consciousness goes all the way down
versus the traditional perennial
philosophy idea that consciousness only
later emerges either when life emerges
out of matter or mind emerges out of
life you know his idea i think you know
is that
every holland has an exterior and an
interior which is the way he puts it
and that consciousness not only goes all
the way down but is kind of like the
origin
and again it sounds like you were kind
of critiquing that but i'm wondering
yeah i could
give you that yeah no i i i'm not i mean
there are sophisticated versions of pan
psychism that are
close enough to naturalism that i'm all
right with um but
there's no way in any level in my
estimation
uh it's not analogous to talk about a
hydrogen atom
having an interior i mean when we use
the word as human beings consciousness
okay uh when i talk about consciousness
i talk about hey i'm conscious now
okay and it does mean i have an interior
but tonight when i get
but you know get buzzed and go to bed
and then i'm out okay that consciousness
is gone so now i'm asleep
okay um and really yes okay i'll flicker
my dreams will flicker on and off all
right but you put me in a coma i'm
basically gone
um and then the eye and so to me you
need a brain
okay to have phenomenology all right
without a brain
i'm pretty suspect now you can
absolutely have friends in
physiologies do cell research you can
say cells have cognition in the sense
that they're complex adaptive systems
that process information
okay so i would argue that yeah they
definitely have functional awareness and
response and there are definite
definitions of consciousness that go
into functional awareness and response
however i don't believe they have any
experiential awareness
and i believe that definitely it stops
there so functional awareness and
response
happens with cells there's they have a
sense
they're robotic essentially in the sense
that in my estimation they would have no
it would have no phenomenological
interior but they do have a sense-making
interior they do
make decisions they have autopilot
complex adaptive functions
that they process but i don't think that
to apply the word consciousness even in
a small amount
makes much sense um for me consciousness
emerges out of the neural functionality
uh of mental behavior which means it
comes out of the animal mental dimension
um and you know i think it happens
actually at the cambrian explosion
and it corresponds to operant behavior
in animals basically
and there are a lot of to me cutting
edge researchers that
are explaining why that is right now
did you have a follow-up ron no no that
was that was helpful and
and sort of what i suspected was close
to your view
so thank you sure thanks for the
question great
um next is cadella and after that um
i'm going to read ernesto's
hi greg can you hear me i can cadel hey
yeah great talk my main my main question
i guess
is about maybe at first i would ask
do you consider theory of knowledge of
meta language
and if so how does it relate to other
meta languages basically languages which
attempt to map
our own knowledge great
yeah i mean i think that's a good way of
describing it uh you know what
what i i know you're familiar with big
history
um and you know i i'm sympathetic to
what they're trying to do sort of
develop a meta view of natural science
i'm basically
with the tree of knowledge uh i'm
offering a more precise
language system and one that solves the
problem of psychology
and then and then in doing that then we
can say we can
there is a way to talk about matter life
mind and culture
with consensual agreement we can talk
about their inner relations in a
particular way
and uh you know i published a an article
talking about yeah hey let's correspond
this with big history
um there are lots of then other language
systems that i know you know that i'm
really interested in
uh like uh well certainly integrals one
example but
you know xyzac's uh language system uh
you know you got me hooked on hegel i'm
going back to hegel and making certain
kinds of connections along those lines
um but i do i really do see
sort of this meta-modern uh sensibility
happening
where people are coming together with
what i would call an integrated
pluralistic sensibility and what i mean
by that there's an appreciation for
difference
but there's also a central uh force of
integration
uh and looking to correspond uh
different systems not so much in a
competitive
hey you have to talk this way but here's
a system that makes sense
do you see it your way you know what are
the things that we're saying to be
real what's the void uh to use the
language you and i would be familiar
with
uh and then you know and knowing that no
system is going to be sort of the
absolute
truth but the correspondence between
meta systems is something i'm very
interested in
okay thanks that's that's a lot of
points to go off in the future
so thanks
um i'm going to read out the next
questions from ernesto
um it's a slightly different take this
is going to be interesting
um just a few days ago a nobel prize was
a board awarded to roger penrose for his
theories about the big bang
not being the start of everything so far
it would seem like the tok theory in all
human
scientific knowledge has been restricted
to events after the big bang considering
that the bible verses you showed suggest
that god
equals language and that those predate
everything
um and here's the question is religion
the only way
to work with that which could have
existed since before
or has given rise to current physical
reality
and any knowledge we can gather
scientifically
or by means of our mind
huh that's a okay that's a let me unpack
that a little bit good question
um so yeah let me
well let me let me contextualize what i
think of in terms of human knowledge and
this
this can uh bridge off at cadell's point
as i've said many times
it depends on what you mean by the big
bang but if the big bang
i'll start with one comment if the big
bang turns out to be wrong
okay much of the edifice of my
justification system
definitely is built on some of that and
then my arguments are
wrong or at least need to be
significantly updated so the first thing
i want to say is our knowledge systems
are fallible
um that's inevitable nature of science
uh you make certain suppositions
there are variants on the big bang i
want to be clear that
lots of different variants that would be
legitimate
um there are explorations now on what
what is behind the big bang
um can we actually understand that the
universe is a function of matter
anti-matter waves
uh and just this is that there's an
implosion and then an explosion
you know that stuff is not stuff that i
have followed
for me right now sort of the uh
basically the big bang seems to be an
epistemological and ontological horizon
um in relationship to the question of
god um
for me what what it what the big bang
comes out of is the void
okay um and that ontological
epistemological horizon
can then uh basically then is where god
can be found
uh as it were um in terms of my point
about in the beginning there was the
word
um i was really making the reference uh
which certainly does connect to god and
and those kinds of elements i was really
making the reference that jordan
peterson did
which is that the fall in in paradise
and eating from the apple really is
about the emergence
in humans of self-consciousness and
propositional knowledge
and the judgment uh and justification
about what is good and evil
and of course then that's going to give
rise to our narratives about god
i wasn't necessarily making an
ontological or metaphysical claim about
god per se
ernesto did you have a follow-up
okay cool um
greg this is a a little bit of a
different question
okay it's from and he's also asked for
me to read it out
this came up today in conversation if an
animal has consciousness is it capable
of aesthetic
ethical and poetic processes are animals
moral or
amoral great
great question um you know i generally
think of animals as a
moral um and and i think that for
morality does require
self-conscious justification on a social
stage okay
and what i mean by that is is that um
you know there is something radically
different that happens at the
self-conscious level
when you start to explain your actions
to others and are forced to give
accounts
and while animals have very
sophisticated
communication systems and certainly
engage in some levels of feedback
there's nothing in my estimation in the
animal kingdom that has the flexibility
openness and fluidity of human language
nor is there much in the way of
indication that the level of their
self-conscious reflection
uh would then enable questions and
philosophies and ideas about morality
okay now that said um i certainly see
lots of proto-morality in
primates and what i mean by that is
there's definitely a distinction
between an attitude of care of an idea
about what
fairness is an idea about reciprocity
ideas about self-deception
and frustration um there's an enormous
amount of
what we would immediately identify as
ethical behavior
and uh less than ethical behavior uh and
project on to that for example
if you're familiar with bonobos bonobos
are a particular kind of
related to a chimpanzee but you know
different they're much more matriarchal
they're also
tend to be much more cooperative much
more giving much less
aggressive and vindictive uh male chimps
can be really aggressive and vindictive
and hostile and
and manipulative in certain regards and
and downright vicious at times
um we can see and we can see the
responses of other creatures
of other bonobos and chimpanzees to
those kinds of behaviors
in ways that are more complicated than
just operant uh reward there's a sense
of
fairness there's a sense of reciprocity
there's a sense of trust there's a sense
of pride and shame
i think in these creatures i don't think
you need full self-consciousness for
pride and shame i can explain why
but all of that again gives rise to an
intuitive affective phenomenological
element that grounds all of our senses
of morality
however what they don't have is an
explicit system of justification
that they can feed back on ask questions
about well is this really moral or not
and for me a full moral creature has got
to be
operating at that level of explicit
feedback
um peter peters forrester dropped an
article into the chat about there's a
recent study
um crows are capable of conscious
thought science demonstrates for the
first time
yeah unbelievable so yeah and by
conscious thought there's no
so crows uh lots of animals demonstrate
self-reflective awareness
okay at the proto level uh and we've
done that's uh gordon golov
developed a test uh and for determining
whether or not an animal can recognize
itself
in the mirror um that we are seeing the
expansion of conscious
thought and by that awareness of whether
or not the animal knows or not
uh there's a study with the bumblebees
that just came out
uh that bumblebees can do cross-modal
sense recognition
okay so if you if you if it touches
something
and then it sees something it can
recognize the thing that it's touched
by what it saw in a bumblebee okay so
there's no doubt that we are seeing
serious cognitive capacities and as far
as i'm concerned absolutely crows will
have experiential consciousness
they'll have deliberation they'll even
be able to have some demonstration of i
know this
relative to this that's very different
than self-conscious justification i will
say
okay so conscious thought does when they
say they're conscious they don't mean
like
conscious like i'm right now saying well
should i say this or should we go on to
the next question i'm gonna reflect on
that
uh explicit intersubjective narration is
very different
but an intuition of self what one knows
what one doesn't even deception of other
animals
uh the higher animals so that and crows
are some of the smartest creatures
around no doubt which is kind of
surprising given the brain size i mean
we're all trying to find out about this
i mean this is you know ethology and
comparative psycho i prefer the term
comparative psychology
um or now the term cognitive ethology is
very common
um but you know great stuff and and i
think it
behooves us to embrace we've undershot
uh generally animal cognitive conscious
capacities in my estimation
i think it behooves us to look and
embrace uh but it's also the case
sometimes people overshoot and say oh
they're just as smart as also they have
language with us it's like
no just look at the last 50 000 years
you know something was a game changer in
the way we behaved
alex had a question to that his question
is
is language necessary for morality a lot
of videos show animals helping each
other out even when it's in their
species
well again it depends a lot on what you
define by morality you know
some people talk about rightness some
people talk about goodness people have
different theories of ethics
okay if you have an absolute view of
ethics absolutist being
that you know that throughout the
universe good and evil have existed star
wars has an absolute view
of ethics there's a good life force
where you make sacrifice for the good of
the commons or good of other people
uh the ability to do that and to care
about others is the definition of the
good
if you're selfish and you injure and you
injure others just for your own selfish
and pleasurable game
then you're part of the dark force if
you have an idea that the cosmos is
governed by an absolute
force of ethics then of course animals
demonstrate uh
care uh they demonstrate you know
morality in that sense
um that's not necessarily my definition
of morality i believe proto-morality
emerges as a function of
relationship dynamics around cooperation
and competition
about dialectics of self and other about
capacities to empathize and willingness
is to empathize uh an empathetic
view that is self-sacrificing is the is
the phenomenological ground of our
morality but we want to then basically
be able to say hey
well what actually is moral uh and then
once you do that and then you have a
i have a universalist constructionist
view of morality
which basically means we're grounded in
this notion
and that's why we can get an enormous
amount of agreement among people about
what is morality
but it is also the case that we bring it
into being
and have the freedom to make judgments
about what is morality
rather than we discover its essence as
existing in the universe before we came
along
um we have a couple more questions but
there's not so much more time today
what were you thinking greg do you think
getting back to
the presentation would make sense today
carrying it on
next time let's keep talking all right
we have 15 minutes let's keep talking
and uh so i certainly if i don't know if
there's a communication process but if
people
want to see the garden they want to talk
about consciousness they want more tree
of knowledge
uh there's metasite tech you know the
whole thing's available you know
we can i do classes on this thing so
there's a lot of different directions we
can go
i'd love to be responsive to where
people's interests are what feels alive
for them um
if you guys want to drop it into the
chat um greg was talking about the third
session would be with zach so
i think that leaves two other sessions
um a few
of the topics that greg's mentioned like
the metapsych tech or the justification
hypothesis well what speaks to mind i
think that could be helpful as greg just
said
um
peter sforza had a question that kind of
takes it back
to tok and psychology um you don't want
if you don't mind fielding that
uh peter did you want to ask you a
question i'd love to yeah
thanks angen uh yeah i appreciate this
greg
i've came across your work um you know
being frustrated with sort of the limits
of
uh modeling simulation visualization and
trying to resolve different
competing models and hypotheses and so i
read your
i found your paper which i think is part
of the backstory to the tree of
knowledge
and i was wondering if you could speak
to how
within the field and discipline of
psychology you
saw two major competing hypotheses and
paraphrasing and worked to resolve those
that i think the method there is a
useful
and general purpose kind of sense-making
and meaning
tool yeah thanks for that and and so
i do believe that that's the case i
think you see it like in peter's
leadership here
because what happened to me uh was as
follows so i came up
in my undergrad i bought the empirical
version of reality for psychology
okay so that's mainstream academic
psychology you take a psych 101 course
they say psychology is this field it's
about the science of behavior and mental
process
and then they drop in and they
immediately say well we don't you know
now it's about science and then they
basically teach you that
science is about empirical epistemology
okay which i love science i'm a hardcore
scientist at one level
um but what you realize over time
okay is that uh facts are theory laden
okay that that facts don't just exist
findings don't exist thomas kuhn of
course made a famous philosopher
historian of science you know talked
about paradigms and really
facts reside in paradigms i tell the
story when i was at the university of
pennsylvania
um i worked under back uh and jr t beck
he's a famous
uh psychiatrist actually although he's
totally influential in psychology
for cognitive psychotherapy and we were
treating individuals who
made a suicide recently made a suicide
attempt brought all those individuals in
we ran the study for a year and it was a
complete failure
for a year um why these are individuals
who were
a quarter of them were homeless really
really tough scenarios
uh 75 percent made less than 15 000
a year in philadelphia so think about
living off of that um
seventy-five percent uh had substance
use problems multiple
disorders and by definition they came in
making a suicide attempt
my job was to run this study um we ran
it for a while i figured out a few
things about how to get people
in but then i couldn't get them in uh to
uh stay and then bec learned about that
sort of blew up we all had a big meeting
and we changed the study in lots of
different ways okay
um and i'll get back to your peter your
question in a second this just makes the
point
we changed the study in a wide variety
of different ways uh
and then we reinstituted it and lo and
behold it was a success
now how did we change the study well
virtually everything we did had a social
work or humanistic flavor to it
okay that is we created wrap-around
services we maintain contact with them
i actually took over some of the therapy
i hired and showed how to do
people to do we did all of these things
okay
and if we had done all of those things
in the context of say having consulted
a professor of social work they would
have come along and said oh my god
the social work intervention is what
makes all the difference i mean you have
the data right there
okay well in becky and the land when the
focus is on becky and cognitive therapy
all of those changes are interpreted as
tweaks
necessary to deliver the intervention so
we didn't write them up at all
i just talked about them when i made a
presentation so
all of those efforts were seen as error
and necessary tweaks
yet if we had a different paradigm we
would have said that's the central
intervention
okay and so what that shows and then
what i learned in my graduate training
was gosh
sometimes i look at somebody and yeah
those negative thoughts really do seem
to be feeding back on some people
but sometimes i'm working with somebody
and their their thoughts seem okay but
they're deep
dark feelings they seem so defended
against them
okay that they seem really shallow in
other words i want to go a deep dive
into a young in
depth psychology frame and other times
the damn
family system is so chaotic i think
they're suffering you know if anybody
saw the
ordinary uh people it's a great movie in
1980s like
really the guy looks like he's this one
that's got ptsd and depression but it's
the mom
and the family system that's all f'd up
okay so family systems view is
absolutely central
so over and over again i saw all these
different frames of reference
uh sometimes they were sort of these
iconic exemplars
and then the question is well how do you
move through them how do you steel man
them
okay how do you respect that perspective
without necessarily getting trapped and
then defined against
okay and that's a really key area and i
think that what like the soa tries to do
and all these meme wars is everybody
gets committed to their virgin reality
as if it's the only version of reality
no it's actually an island of a version
of reality in a
sea of different possible versions of
reality so wake up to that
okay now there that does you can't stop
there from my vantage point because then
all you basically get is eclectic chaos
all right so then the question is is
there a meta superordinate level
upon which you can actually see themes
you know so you have a thesis and
antithesis is there any kind of
synthesis
uh and that's what i started hunting for
uh for me my first step then was
i had to get out of the psychotherapy
and in back into the science
i got back into evolutionary psychology
um which then provided me a step back i
was actually a meta so i could see
actually all the major paradigms at
least adopt him and
so there's a line of agreement um
unfortunately from my vantage point
evolutionary psychology was committed to
too many different
assumptions that were rigid that got
itself defined against like cultural
psychology
and behavioral learning psychology in
problematic ways and so i tried to avoid
that
um and then i got lucky i had a set of
insights and
boom and then when the things were
tweaked and then all of a sudden
i could see that everybody was saying
something valid um but at the same time
i had a position where i could harmonize
it well
then that's where i'd want to go i've
been very disappointed with the academy
because the academy claims that it's
after these kinds of things
but the fact of the matter is it's all
about the contingencies that the academy
is now structured under
okay so for me to come out and say you
know psychology actually nobody knows
what the f psychology is
and its commitment to empirical
eclecticism actually
means that basically what you're doing
is you're hiring full professors
to build super sophisticated empirical
sand castles
okay what i mean by that is they have
their operational definitions
they find what they need they get all
their funding they get their doc
students and yeah you can get like
growth mindset and it's really
interesting
but it sits in a particular relatively
narrow paradigm
and then what's going to happen
somebody's going to come along they're
redefining i mean growth mindset
basically is like
interior locus of control that roger did
back in 1955 for the love of god
okay we've known about this kind of
stuff they just put it in to put the
lips different lipstick on the pig and
get it out there but the fact of the
matter is that we're not getting
different
cumulative elements so my response to
you is
going to hold different positions want
to do it non-defensively
want to steal ban various elements when
you see contradiction wonder
about a higher order synthesis and also
look at how trapped the academy is
in relationships how entrenched it is
and once it gets established
man it's it's really really hard to move
yeah yeah it sounds like um
more towards like a pluralistic
epistemology and
i agree in the academy it's challenged
with the incentive structures and
whatnot um
in the modeling simvis community we kind
of think about composability
interoperability as a grand challenge
and so the follow up would be you showed
in your gestalt uh the movement from
data
information knowledge wisdom and in the
mod sim vis let's say we have
architectures for data data
architectures info architectures
knowledge architectures
what do you think about wisdom
architectures in that
um what would that mean in this kind of
pluralistic epistemology
sure uh i will say i want to be clear
i'm a meta-modernist not a postmodernist
okay so post-modernism just embraces the
pluralism
uh but then it through usually a
critique of
modernism and the injustices that are
associated with that
and then that embraces marginalized
pluralistic
uh uh systems which at a justice level
is good but
in and of itself then it serves as a
critique function and then it devolves
uh ken wilber does this brilliantly he
sees this we definitely need an
integrated pluralism
okay so it's an integrated pluralistic
epistemology not everything goes it's
not just
whatever your epistemology it's got to
be anchored to certain principles
um for me what i then say is well what
are the ultimate metacultural
justification systems i have a
saying that i use that organizes my
thinking be
that which enhances dignity and
well-being with integrity
okay uh that's in the garden uh dignity
it comes from i'll say this quickly from
the universal declaration of human
rights the most uh consensual document
ever agreed upon
and what that does is it justifies
people's respect uh respecting people
and then that legitimizes
justice and rights so it serves that
unbelievably crucial function
well-being is the mission of the world
health organization took a hit and
coveted but nonetheless
um well-being is a complicated construct
that i've thought a lot about it's the
seventh branch on the tree is how do you
define what well-being is
human well-being and then we want to
expand that out to well-being ultimately
of gaia i.e the earth and all the
creatures in it
uh and then integrity refers to accuracy
honor truth
uh along those lines so uh for me what
i'm looking at when i'm looking at a
system
ultimately is i'm going to take a step
and use my universal morality judgments
along those values to see
you know things that don't conform in a
big way you know
in no political without making a
political statement at all i
i cannot stand trump because he violates
the intellectual integrity principle
okay so it's a big three value and as a
function of that
uh then then i'm al it's like oh my gosh
so i for myself
i do have a big three where i think you
need and not everyone needs to have
those
big three exactly but if you have love
if you have trust if you have freedom i
mean there's certain kinds of ultimate
meta values
agape that really do set the stage for
playing
uh well with each other across the
global scale and i embrace those things
brilliant and inspiring thank you
um greg we only got a couple more
minutes today
um i'm curious if you have any closing
thoughts
if you kind of wanted to prep us um for
the following week and if
there was any way you could share the
slides
oh absolutely yeah um well first off i
love the
opportunity um i i love this space
you know peter it's a great space okay
um we have a lot of work to do people
okay look around
you know uh and and but there are
opportunities
uh for us to find better paths uh so
uh we just need to keep coming out
together figuring out ways to
participate with each other share ideas
figure out how to leverage the ideas
that we have you know
i sent out a note to my lister uh
on the debate day and i said instead of
watching the debate i'm going to watch
john verveiki and jordan hall and
uh christopher and uh guy talk to your
logos
okay because we need to be doing
different things
so that's my fundamental thing we need
to be working to enhance dignity and
well-being with integrity
and seeking sense-making systems that do
that so that's my pitch
um i'm gonna take peter and thanks greg
all right
beautiful thank you anjan and thank you
greg for
coming to estoa uh really looking
forward for the next session
and very grateful that you are here uh
since making residence
for this month um so a couple of events
and you might be interested in this one
uh greg we're launching something called
um we just thought in the chats
called communitas club uh me and
margaret are going to lead this series
uh and we're going to just investigate
different conversational intersubjective
modalities with a practitioner
maybe even the founder of it where we're
going to talk about it get an
understanding of it and practice it
and it might be even ported in the stoa
like uh
rhea bex box um collective presence or
edwin rush's
empathy circles uh and the first four we
have lined up
i'll put from the chats we have
something called entangled bodies
uh ephemeral group process forest
landry's going to come and talk about
that
really really cool tool called
reflective structure dialogue i'm not
sure if you know that but like
jill the temple she's bringing that into
the academia and then
we have circling in toronto's circling
practitioner taylor's going to come and
do that
so check that out you can rcp the launch
of that session which is next week
um another event i think would be good
to plug uh rain do you want to plug the
the hollow the other chancemaker in
residence
that's coming this friday sure um
i will be emceeing the holo the
beginning of bonita roy's new
series from what i understand
she is um putting forward this
image of the hollow as a gathering place
as um something that's maybe a bit
uh countercultural in in how it
engages in embodied sense making that's
about all i
i know so um yeah i would love to see
you there
great yeah it's gonna be a lot of fun um
so here's uh more events on the website
the patreon and the sub stack
um that being said i hope to see
everyone next week
same time same day thank you
and great can you hold on for like five
minutes that we're just gonna want to
debrief
afterwards okay perfect play some good
music
while people trickle out